Finding Aid for James A. Brown papers, 1872-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James A. Brown papers 1872-1974
Brown, James A.
(in 4 boxes)
3.5 linear feet
8574 Aa 2
Papers of the Rev. James A. Brown, Michigan Methodist minister, and his wife Winifred Croel Brown. Correspondence, diaries, sermons, photographs and other materials relating in part to their pastorate in Elsie, Michigan, life during the depression; include comments on farming conditions, politics, and the effects of prohibition.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Alfred C. Wooll (donor no. 6900 ) in March 1983.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Reverend James A. Brown (ca. 1888-1951) of Lyons, Michigan, was graduated from Albion College in 1917, ordained a Deacon of the Methodist Church in the same year, and an Elder in 1919. Winifred Croel Brown (1886-1976), also of Lyons, was a 1911 graduate of Central Michigan Normal School. The couple adopted one daughter, Gladys Brown Wooll.
During his ministry Rev. Brown served parishes in Delta, Tompkins and Winfield, Hanover and Moscow, Hubbardston, Remus, Elsie, and Constantine. In 1944 the Browns retired to Ionia. James Brown died in 1951; Winifred in 1976.
The James Brown collection consists of papers of James Brown, his wife Winifred Croel Brown and several relatives of James Brown. It includes correspondence, diaries, sermons, photographs and other materials relating in part to their pastorate in Elsie, Michigan, life during the depression. In addition to information on family and church matters, the papers include comments on farming conditions, politics, and the effects of prohibition. The collection has been arranged into three series: the papers of James A. Brown, Winifred Croel Brown, and the extended Brown Family.
Subjects:
Brown, James A., ca. 1888-1951.; Clergy--Michigan--Elsie.; Depressions--1929--Michigan--Elsie.; Elsie (Mich.); Farm life--Michigan--Elsie.; Methodist Church (U.S.)--Michigan--Elsie.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Prohibition--Michigan.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Gettysburg National Military Park (Pa.); Veterans--Michigan.
Contributors:
Brown, Winifred Croel, 1886-1976.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Sermons.
- James A. Brown
  James Brown's papers consist of correspondence, diaries, conference reports, and sermons. The correspondence and diaries tell of church activities, the management of the Brown Family farm, and other family concerns. Interesting comments are made about events and personalities of the times, the depression, farming conditions, politics, and prohibition. There are conference reports for scattered dates from 1921 to 1941 and sermons delivered from 1926 to 1943. Sermons are identified as baccalaureate sermons, children's sermonettes, and general sermons.
  - Correspondence
    - Undated, 1913, 1915-1916, 1918, 1920-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1924 (Box 1)
    - 1925 (Box 1)
    - 1926 (Box 1)
    - 1927 (Box 1)
    - 1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931 (Box 1)
    - 1932 (Box 1)
    - 1933 (Box 1)
    - 1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935 (Box 1)
    - 1936 (Box 1)
    - 1937 (Box 1)
      (1938 missing)
    - 1939-1949 (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - 1907, 1908 (Box 1)
    - 1909, 1910 (Box 1)
    - 1911, 1912, 1913 (Box 1)
    - 1919-1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921, 1922 (Box 1)
    - 1923, 1924 (Box 1)
    - 1925, 1926 (Box 1)
    - 1927, 1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929, 1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931, 1932, 1933 (Box 1)
    - 1934, 1935 (Box 1)
    - 1936 (Box 1)
    - January 1937-September 1938 (Box 1)
    - September 1938-July 1940 (Box 1)
    - July 1940-March 1942 (Box 2)
    - April 1942-September 1943 (Box 2)
    - September 1943-June 1945 (Box 2)
    - June 1945-June 1946 (Box 2)
    - June 1946-December 1947 (Box 2)
    - January 1948-February 1950 (Box 2)
    - February 1950-March 1951 (Box 2)
  - Expense Account (Box 2)
  - November 1917-May 1918 (Box 2)
  - Quarterly Conference Reports 1921, 1923, 1929, 1935, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Record of Sermons 1930-1936, reminiscences written 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Sermons
    - Baccalaureate Sermons 1926, 1929, 1930, 1932-1933, 1939, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Children's Sermonettes 1926-1929, 1940 (Box 2)
    - General
      - 1913-1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1943 (Box 2)
      - Undated (Box 2)
- Winifred Croel Brown
  Included in Winifred Croel Brown's papers are clippings relating to her service as an American Red Cross Gray Lady, diaries, a scrapbook, a sermon written in 1910, and a copy of her will. The diaries give an account of her daily life as the wife of a minister serving rural parishes and of her later years as a widow. The scrapbook consists mostly of poetry, but does include a few clippings relating to residents of Lyons and Ionia.
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Diaries
    - 1932, 1933, 1934 (Box 2)
    - 1935, 1936, 1945 (also 1973, 1974) (Box 3)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 3)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 3)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 3)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - 1957 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1962 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - 1963-1967, 1968-1972 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook (Box 3)
  - Sermon, 1910 "Courage and Enthusiasm" (Box 3)
  - Will August 1, 1951 (Box 3)
- Brown Family
  The Brown Family series includes papers relating to James Brown's uncle, brother, and parents. Charles Franklin Brown was James' brother. His papers include a certificate of membership in the Ancient Order of Gleaners and a copy of his will. The papers of James' parents, Joseph and Annie Brown, include marriage and citizenship certificates, an inventory of their estate, and papers relating to the administration of the estate.
  James Brown was the administrator of the estate of his uncle, Charles Brown. Included in the Charles Brown papers are correspondence between James and the attorney for the estate, renters of property owned by the estate, and family members who were heirs, an account book, an inventory of the estate, and legal papers relating to disposition of the property.
  - Charles Franklin Brown (certificate of membership in Ancient Order of Gleaners 1918 and Will, June 7, 1920) (Box 3)
  - Joseph C. and Annie Huestis Brown
    - Certificates of Marriage and Citizenship 1872, 1880 (Box 3)
    - Papers relating to estate 1915-1916 (Box 3)
  - Papers relating to properties 1916, 1927, 1930-1931, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Charles Brown Estate
    - Correspondence 1930-1940, 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Papers 1930-1940 (Box 3)
    - Charles Brown estate correspondence and other papers 1930s (Box 4)
  - Photographs: (Box 4)
    The Photographs are chiefly of a visit to Gettysburg battlefield, 1922 with Brown's father-in-law, William A. Croel, who served there with the 5th Michigan Cavalry during the Civil War and portraits.